<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Alex Bowers&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>https://zando.io/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Alex Bowers&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 21:35:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://zando.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using HA Proxy for SaaS systems - Custom Domains</title>
      <link>https://zando.io/post/haproxy-saas-custom-domains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 21:35:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zando.io/post/haproxy-saas-custom-domains/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;
.hljs {
    white-space: pre;
    overflow-x: auto;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common problem with setting up a SaaS system is how to manage the customers on a custom domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy when everybody enters your system through &lt;code&gt;example.com&lt;/code&gt;, and even &lt;code&gt;account-name.example.com&lt;/code&gt; wildcards, but what if your system offers the ability to have a custom domain such as &lt;code&gt;zando.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a problem we had at Shopblocks, and I tried a few ways of solving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are experienced with HA Proxy and just want to see the configuration, skip to the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to experience the journey with me, read on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first involved using Ansible to create a new virtual host for Apache and then reloading the apache server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This worked, however, performance became an issue pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registrations were taking a long time, sometimes up to a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Ansible with Apache also had no guarantee of consistency, if a server was offline during the registration process then that server didn&amp;rsquo;t have the virtual host, and could not resolve the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fix the consistency issue we sharing the virtual hosts across the platform on a mounted drive using NFS. The performance of the mounted drive was not majorly affected by this move, but the performance was still an issue on the process side. We had solved the consistency issue, but we still had a couple of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we enforce HTTPS on all requests, our load balancer could not utilise proxying with the clients IP address. This meant that our logs from Apache, and internally in our system, all would have the load balancers private IP and not the clients IP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also still had the performance issue. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t really acceptable, and so we wanted a completely different approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were already using HA proxy for our load balancing, and we knew that HA proxy could terminate SSL connections and modify requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we could solve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSL connection terminating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retaining the client IP address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unique Virtual Hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of Ansible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we should be in a much better position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would allow us to more easily perform upgrades on our application servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possibilities for upgrades were plentiful; whether that be changing from Apache to Nginx, adding more servers to the clusters easily or even moving to completely different architecture in the backend (for example, NodeJS instead of Apache + PHP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sorts of upgrades are now much simpler to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed like we were going down the correct route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first problem to solve is forcing HTTP to HTTPS redirects. This is very easy to do in HA Proxy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend http
    bind :80

    redirect scheme https code 301

frontend https
    bind :443

    # We will fill this in later
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are listening for requests on port 80 and port 443.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any request that comes in on port 80 will be redirected with a &lt;code&gt;301 Permanent Redirect&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now done with any HTTP requests. Everything from now on is HTTPS only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that all of our traffic is HTTPS, we need to terminate those requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Shopblocks, all new accounts start with a couple of &lt;code&gt;myshopblocks.com&lt;/code&gt; subdomains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a wildcard SSL certificate available that covers all of these domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers can also setup a custom domain. This gets provided with a Lets Encrypt certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allowing Lets Encrypt certificates in this setup is a topic of its own, but the gist is you need to get the certificate in &lt;code&gt;pem&lt;/code&gt; format, which involves concatonating the &lt;code&gt;private key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ceritifcate&lt;/code&gt; together into a flat directory file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend https
    bind :443 ssl crt /path/to/certificates

    # We will fill this in later
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This directory of certificates must be flat, contain at least 1 certificate that is valid, and be in &lt;code&gt;.pem&lt;/code&gt; format. The filename of the certificate does not matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, that this method uses SNI headers from the request, and so some requests from old browsers, for example Android 2.3, may not return with the correct certificate, and instead take the first certificate it finds. This is not a major issue, since the systems that do not use SNI are largely outdated and less commonly used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that all of our traffic is HTTPS and is being terminated, we need to load balance the requests and send them through to our web servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend https
    bind :443 ssl crt /path/to/certificates

    use_backend core

backend core
    balance roundrobin

    server WEB_HOSTNAME_01 10.20.30.40:80 check
    server WEB_HOSTNAME_02 10.20.30.41:80 check
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have 2 servers defined in our backend named &lt;code&gt;core&lt;/code&gt;. The backend name does not matter, and is used as an identifier between the &lt;code&gt;use_backend&lt;/code&gt; and the backend itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two servers are being referenced using a private network IP. You can use either public or private network IP&amp;rsquo;s, however I would suggest private networking so that you can have finer control and limit direct access to the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the SSL has already been terminated in the load balancer, we now have a plain HTTP request which we will send through on port 80 to our web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our traffic is now going through the load balancer and hitting a web server, however you are probably getting the 000-default page in apache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is that your request is still coming through on &lt;code&gt;zando.io&lt;/code&gt; instead of a domain name that the apache server knows how to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fix this issue we need to modify the headers sent through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has some caveats, such as not being able to use the HTTP_HOST server variables in PHP as expected. There are ways around that, but it is worth keeping in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to map the request through to &lt;code&gt;system.example.com&lt;/code&gt; in this example. In reality you can set this to any domain, whether you control it or not since no DNS lookups take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;backend core
    ...

    http-request set-header Host system.example.com

    ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domain you choose to replace &lt;code&gt;system.example.com&lt;/code&gt; needs to be recognised by your apache virtual host on port 80.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are now getting the correct page, but your system does not know which domain was originally requested, and by extension, what the customer&amp;rsquo;s ID is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fix this, we will need a map of all domains to a customer ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is stored as a simple key =&amp;gt; value pair in a text file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;domain1.com 1
domain2.com 2
domain3.com 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;domain1.com&lt;/code&gt; belongs to customer with an ID of &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is going to be referred to as our &lt;code&gt;customer.map&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a new customer or domain gets added to your system, you simply need to append to this file, and reload haproxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend https
    ...

    http-request set-header X-Customer-ID %[req.hdr(host),lower,map_str(/path/to/customer.map)]

    ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will set the &lt;code&gt;X-Customer-ID&lt;/code&gt; header based on the &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; matching the &lt;code&gt;host&lt;/code&gt;. You want to ensure that your &lt;code&gt;customer.map&lt;/code&gt; file is all lowercase, since the &lt;code&gt;lower&lt;/code&gt; function in use will convert the request header to lowercase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have the system assigning the &lt;code&gt;X-Customer-ID&lt;/code&gt; for domains that the map file contains, but if it does not contain a file, the &lt;code&gt;X-Customer-ID&lt;/code&gt; is set, but empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is okay in your system, then leave it as it is, however if you do not want to resolve requests at all for any domains you do not recognise then above the &lt;code&gt;http-request&lt;/code&gt; line, you can add the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend https
    ...

    acl is_customer hdr(host),lower,map_str(/path/to/customer.map) -m found

    http-request silent-drop unless is_customer

    http-request set-header ...

    ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the connection will drop immediately for any domain requests not recognised in the &lt;code&gt;customer.map&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We determine whether somebody is a customer using an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Access_control_list&#34;&gt;Access Control List (acl)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a variable called &lt;code&gt;is_customer&lt;/code&gt; which will be a variable based on the &lt;code&gt;found&lt;/code&gt; method specified by the &lt;code&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt; flag used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can assume that if the domain is found in the list, they are a customer of ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting that all together you should have something that looks like the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;frontend http
    bind :80

    redirect scheme https code 301

frontend https
    bind :443 ssl crt /path/to/certificates

    acl is_customer hdr(host),lower,map_str(/path/to/customer.map) -m found

    http-request silent-drop unless is_customer

    http-request set-header X-Customer-ID %[req.hdr(host),lower,map_str(/path/to/customer.map)]

    use_backend core

backend core
    balance roundrobin

    http-request set-header Host system.example.com

    server WEB_HOSTNAME_01 10.20.30.40:80 check
    server WEB_HOSTNAME_02 10.20.30.41:80 check 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the basics of setting up a SaaS resolver in HA proxy and passing it through to Apache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, feel free to send me a message on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bowersbros&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bowersbros+haproxy_blog_post@gmail.com&#34;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hugojmd&#34;&gt;Hugojmd&lt;/a&gt; for proof reading and spotting mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Zend Module Entry</title>
      <link>https://zando.io/post/explaining-zend-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 22:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zando.io/post/explaining-zend-module/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting Started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hello World&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explaining Zend Module Entry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://zando.io/writing-a-hello-world-php-7-extension/&#34;&gt;last blog post&lt;/a&gt; I skirted past what &lt;code&gt;zend_module_entry&lt;/code&gt; does, and just put the code there. I&amp;rsquo;m going to attempt to explain it with its many &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I put in the Hello World extension:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;zend_module_entry hello_module_entry = {  
        STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER,
        PHP_HELLO_EXTNAME,
        hello_functions,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        PHP_HELLO_VERSION,
        STANDARD_MODULE_PROPERTIES,
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This structure comes from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/1c295d4a9ac78fcc2f77d6695987598bb7abcb83/Zend/zend_modules.h#L73-L102&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;struct _zend_module_entry {
    unsigned short size;
    unsigned int zend_api;
    unsigned char zend_debug;
    unsigned char zts;
    const struct _zend_ini_entry *ini_entry;
    const struct _zend_module_dep *deps;
    const char *name;
    const struct _zend_function_entry *functions;
    int (*module_startup_func)(INIT_FUNC_ARGS);
    int (*module_shutdown_func)(SHUTDOWN_FUNC_ARGS);
    int (*request_startup_func)(INIT_FUNC_ARGS);
    int (*request_shutdown_func)(SHUTDOWN_FUNC_ARGS);
    void (*info_func)(ZEND_MODULE_INFO_FUNC_ARGS);
    const char *version;
    size_t globals_size;
#ifdef ZTS
    ts_rsrc_id* globals_id_ptr;
#else
    void* globals_ptr;
#endif
    void (*globals_ctor)(void *global);
    void (*globals_dtor)(void *global);
    int (*post_deactivate_func)(void);
    int module_started;
    unsigned char type;
    void *handle;
    int module_number;
    const char *build_id;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;standard-module-header&#34;&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a macro that fills in a few of the fields for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few of these macros defined, these are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/1c295d4a9ac78fcc2f77d6695987598bb7abcb83/Zend/zend_modules.h#L43&#34;&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER_EX&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/1c295d4a9ac78fcc2f77d6695987598bb7abcb83/Zend/zend_modules.h#L44&#34;&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These macros fill the fields size, zend_api, zend_debug, zts and, ini_entry and deps for the non _EX header&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER is used when you don&amp;rsquo;t have any dependencies, if you have dependencies then use &lt;code&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER_EX&lt;/code&gt; instead, and it will leave out a &lt;code&gt;deps&lt;/code&gt; field that you can fill in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php-hello-extname&#34;&gt;PHP_HELLO_EXTNAME&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the name of our extension. We registered this as a constant in &lt;code&gt;hello.h&lt;/code&gt;, you could simply put a string in here. This field is &lt;strong&gt;required&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hello-functions&#34;&gt;hello_functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a reference to the structure of zend_function_entry that we put in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;zend_function_entry hello_functions[] = {  
            PHP_FE(hello_world, NULL)
        PHP_FE_END
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;zend_function_entry&lt;/code&gt; is just a structure containing one or more &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/d8507d4f582997ae3efe074f54900af2936835e6/Zend/zend_API.h#L76&#34;&gt;function definitions&lt;/a&gt;, and ending with a &lt;code&gt;PHP_FE_END&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/d8507d4f582997ae3efe074f54900af2936835e6/Zend/zend_API.h#L98&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-5&#34;&gt;The next 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are ones you won&amp;rsquo;t touch often, unless you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They define, in order,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Module startup function

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Module shutdown function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request startup function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request shutdown function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Info Function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;version-number&#34;&gt;Version Number&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is the version of the extension. This should be provided as a string, though we are using a constant that we defined in &lt;code&gt;hello.h&lt;/code&gt;. There is also a constant &lt;code&gt;NO_VERSION_YET&lt;/code&gt;, which just defines it as &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;standard-module-properties&#34;&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_PROPERTIES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the properties are filled in for you by using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/1c295d4a9ac78fcc2f77d6695987598bb7abcb83/Zend/zend_modules.h#L61&#34;&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_PROPERTIES&lt;/a&gt;. There should be no need for you to fill in these, unless you need to fill in some extension globals, in which case use &lt;code&gt;STANDARD_MODULE_PROPERTIES\_EX&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a Hello World PHP 7 Extension</title>
      <link>https://zando.io/post/hello-world-php-7-extension/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 21:26:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zando.io/post/hello-world-php-7-extension/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting Started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explaining Zend Module Entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-setup&#34;&gt;Getting Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the folder &lt;code&gt;/vagrant&lt;/code&gt; you will want to create a new folder with the name of your extension. I will be calling my extension &lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt; and so my folder will be &lt;code&gt;hello-ext&lt;/code&gt;. This is just convention, and the folder name doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ mkdir /vagrant/hello-ext
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very basic PHP extension requires 3 files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;config.m4
src/hello.c
src/hello.h
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;config.m4&lt;/code&gt; extension tells PHP some basic information about your extension. The &lt;code&gt;hello.c&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;hello.h&lt;/code&gt; files are the actual extension itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;actually-writing-the-extension&#34;&gt;Actually writing the extension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;test-case-first&#34;&gt;Test case first&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check whether this actually works, this is a basic PHP file we using to check:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?php
var_dump(extension_loaded(&#39;hello&#39;));

var_dump(hello_world());
?&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At every step of the way through this process, you can re-run this file using &lt;code&gt;php -f /path/to/test/file.php&lt;/code&gt;. If you run this now, you&amp;rsquo;ll see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ php -f test.php
# bool(false)

# Fatal error: Uncaught Error: Call to undefined function hello_world() in /vagrant/test.php:5
# Stack trace:
# #0 {main}
#    thrown in /vagrant/test.php on line 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I hold this file &lt;strong&gt;outside&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;ext&lt;/code&gt; folder. This file isn&amp;rsquo;t part of our extension. We will deal with proper testing at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;config-m4&#34;&gt;config.m4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing we should tell PHP about is the argument to enable the &lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The syntax for the &lt;code&gt;config.m4&lt;/code&gt; file is based on the &lt;code&gt;GNU autoconf&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/autoconf/manual/autoconf.html&#34;&gt;syntax&lt;/a&gt;. Though, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know it really. There will be very few lines involved, and i&amp;rsquo;ll do my best to explain them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments can be left in the &lt;code&gt;config.m4&lt;/code&gt; file using &lt;code&gt;dnl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-autoconf&#34;&gt;dnl Tell PHP about the argument to enable the hello extension

PHP_ARG_ENABLE(hello, Whether to enable the hello world extension, [ --enable-hello   Enable hello world])

if test &amp;quot;$PHP_HELLO&amp;quot; != &amp;quot;no&amp;quot;; then
    PHP_NEW_EXTENSION(hello, src/hello.c, $ext_shared)
fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;dnl&lt;/code&gt; stands for &lt;code&gt;Discard to Next Line&lt;/code&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3371239/autoconf-dnl-vs#comment48017868_3377708&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, including the new line at the end of the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking &lt;code&gt;PHP_ARG_ENABLE(hello, Whether to enable the hello world extension, [ --enable-hello   Enable hello world])&lt;/code&gt; down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PHP_ARG_ENABLE&lt;/code&gt; - Provides &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; with the options and help text seen when running &lt;code&gt;./configure --help&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a &lt;code&gt;PHP_ARG_WITH&lt;/code&gt;, and either &lt;code&gt;ENABLE&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;WITH&lt;/code&gt; should be provided. The difference there is how &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; gets ran, either &lt;code&gt;--with-*&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;--enable-*&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ndash;enable-SOMETHING&lt;/strong&gt; is used for extensions with zero dependencies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ndash;with-SOMETHING&lt;/strong&gt; is used for extensions with dependencies (e.g. it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ndash;enable-pdo, but &amp;ndash;with-pdo-mysql as the latter may depend on libmysqlclient)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to /u/dshafik for clarification on this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every extension should provide at least one or the other with the extension name, so that users can choose whether or not to build the extension into PHP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By convention, &lt;code&gt;PHP_ARG_WITH()&lt;/code&gt; is used for an option which takes a parameter, such as the location of a library or program required by an extension, while &lt;code&gt;PHP_ARG_ENABLE()&lt;/code&gt; is used for an option which represents a simple flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/internals2.buildsys.configunix.php&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt; is just the name of our extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Whether to enable the hello world extension&lt;/code&gt; Not entirely sure what this is for to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ --enable-hello   Enable hello world]&lt;/code&gt; this determines the output for &lt;code&gt;configure --help&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will end up looking something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/ygZBnfD.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;being what was inside the square brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then next bit is literally just a basic &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; check to determine whether or not the the extension is enabled. By default, it will be for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to register the extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PHP_NEW_EXTENSION(hello, src/hello.c, $ext_shared)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first parameter is the name of the extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second parameter is the list of all source files which are part of the extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third parameter should always be $ext_shared, a value which was determined by configure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken, and adapted from the woefully outdated &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/internals2.buildsys.configunix.php&#34;&gt;php guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more parameters, but so far we don&amp;rsquo;t need them, so we will leave them for a different day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the actual extension itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;src-hello-h&#34;&gt;src/hello.h&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is quite basic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;#define PHP_HELLO_EXTNAME &amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;
#define PHP_HELLO_VERSION &amp;quot;0.0.1&amp;quot;

PHP_FUNCTION(hello_world);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are defining two directives, what this allows us to do is use &lt;code&gt;PHP_HELLO_EXTNAME&lt;/code&gt; in place of the actual string &lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt; throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is common practice, so whilst not necessary strictly in this use case, it is a good habit to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first interesting line is &lt;code&gt;PHP_FUNCTION(hello_world);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where we define the header for our function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of the function will go within our &lt;code&gt;hello.c&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;src-hello-c&#34;&gt;src/hello.c&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where things get a little more complicated now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So i&amp;rsquo;ll give you the full file, and then break it down a little:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-c&#34;&gt;#include &amp;lt;php.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;quot;hello.h&amp;quot;

zend_function_entry hello_functions[] = {
            PHP_FE(hello_world, NULL)
        PHP_FE_END
};

zend_module_entry hello_module_entry = {
            STANDARD_MODULE_HEADER,
        PHP_HELLO_EXTNAME,
        hello_functions,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        NULL,
        PHP_HELLO_VERSION,
        STANDARD_MODULE_PROPERTIES,
};

ZEND_GET_MODULE(hello);

PHP_FUNCTION(hello_world) {
            php_printf(&amp;quot;Hello world\
&amp;quot;);
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pasting this in to your file, and then going to the terminal and running the following commands will allow this to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ cd /vagrant/hello-ext
$ phpize
$ ./configure
$ make
$ sudo make install
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing to do is add the extension into your &lt;code&gt;php.ini&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will look like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ini&#34;&gt;extension=hello.so
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, go back to your test file and run it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ php -f test.php
bool(true)
Hello world
NULL
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Fixed typo with response above, thanks to /u/phisch90&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for the hanging &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; is because we are using the &lt;code&gt;printf&lt;/code&gt; function, rather than returning the value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Writing PHP 7 Extensions</title>
      <link>https://zando.io/post/getting-started-with-writing-php-7-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2016 20:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zando.io/post/getting-started-with-writing-php-7-extensions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This blog post is the first in a series of PHP 7 extension building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be joining me on my journey of discovering how extensions are built. I have never written C code before, or looked deeply into PHP internals. I will make mistakes, and I will try my best to correct them as we go along, but if you notice anything, please email me and i&amp;rsquo;ll fix it as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hello World&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explaining Zend Module Entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-vagrant&#34;&gt;Install Vagrant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing we have to do is install PHP 7 as a development version. The best way to do this is to use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vagrantup.com/&#34;&gt;vagrant&lt;/a&gt; box  built by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rasmus_Lerdorf&#34;&gt;Rasmus Lerdorf&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://atlas.hashicorp.com/rasmus/boxes/php7dev&#34;&gt;rasmus/php7dev&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be creating a folder in &lt;code&gt;~/php-extensions/&lt;/code&gt; for each of the extensions created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-vagrant-box&#34;&gt;Install Vagrant Box&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ vagrant init rasmus/php7dev; vagrant up --provider virtualbox
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once that has completed, you will want to &lt;code&gt;vagrant ssh&lt;/code&gt; into the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the series of blog posts will assume we are within the vagrant box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;check-everything-is-ready&#34;&gt;Check everything is ready&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything should be ready, but to check type these commands in and you should see something like the below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ which phpize
# /usr/local/bin/phpize
$ php --version
# PHP 7.0.11-dev (cli) (built: Aug  3 2016 23:41:41) ( NTS DEBUG )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see it all as above then we are ready to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ide-text-editor&#34;&gt;IDE / Text Editor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For PHP extensions you do not need anything special in terms of an IDE, you will be absolutely fine using Sublime Text, Atom, etc. I will be using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jetbrains.com/clion/&#34;&gt;CLion&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jetbrains.com&#34;&gt;JetBrains&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laravel 5.3  - Multiple Migration Paths</title>
      <link>https://zando.io/post/laravel-5.3-multiple-migration-paths/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 21:21:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zando.io/post/laravel-5.3-multiple-migration-paths/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In Laravel 5.3+ there is a new feature that allows for multiple migration paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-should-i-care&#34;&gt;Why should I care?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may not think its that big a deal, but it will help many packages significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A required step previously was to have a publication step, or a copy paste step for the migrations from &lt;code&gt;vendor/package/database/migrations&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;database/migrations&lt;/code&gt;.
This new feature allows the migrations to stay where they are, and not clutter up your migrations folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful because when a package gets a new version, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to possibly have to copy their migrations over again, you want to be able to just run &lt;code&gt;php artisan migrate&lt;/code&gt; and have it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new system it will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;okay-that-sounds-great-how-do-we-use-it&#34;&gt;Okay that sounds great. How do we use it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as you are on Laravel 5.3, it will be enabled for you by default. All you have to do is in a Service Provider (for example, a MigrationsServiceProvider) &lt;code&gt;boot&lt;/code&gt; method, is call &lt;code&gt;$this-&amp;gt;loadMigrationsFrom(&#39;path/to/migrations/folder&#39;)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any subsequent calls to &lt;code&gt;php artisan migrate&lt;/code&gt; will just work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;erm-i-don-t-know-do-i-have-to-do-this&#34;&gt;Erm, I don&amp;rsquo;t know. Do I have to do this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not wish to use this feature, nothing has changed. You can still copy migrations from the package to your database migrations folder if you wish to.
And you do not have to add your migration path in a service provider, that&amp;rsquo;s done for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-should-use-this&#34;&gt;What should use this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be used by any system that wants to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any package you use requires you to pull in their migration files from a specific location, then this is a prime candidate for this to be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your aiming for a modular design.
This is a must to keep the core separate from each module.
Now, your modules are just composer directories living in their own space, and there is no bleeding across the two.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>